{
  "chapter_metadata": {
    "chapter_id": "10.SEMI.4.6",
    "standard": "10",
    "subject": "English",
    "medium": "SEMI",
    "chapter_name": "A Brave Heart Dedicated to Science And Humanity"
  },
  "questions": [
    {
      "question_id": 1,
      "question_type": "MCQ",
      "question": "Who is the central figure of the lesson?",
      "options": [
        {
          "option_id": 1,
          "text": "Rosalind Franklin",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 2,
          "text": "Marie Curie",
          "is_correct": true
        },
        {
          "option_id": 3,
          "text": "Mother Teresa",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 4,
          "text": "Florence Nightingale",
          "is_correct": false
        }
      ],
      "answer": "Marie Curie"
    },
    {
      "question_id": 2,
      "question_type": "MCQ",
      "question": "What element did Marie Curie discover?",
      "options": [
        {
          "option_id": 1,
          "text": "Uranium",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 2,
          "text": "Radium",
          "is_correct": true
        },
        {
          "option_id": 3,
          "text": "Helium",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 4,
          "text": "Neon",
          "is_correct": false
        }
      ],
      "answer": "Radium"
    },
    {
      "question_id": 3,
      "question_type": "MCQ",
      "question": "What was Marie Curie’s original name?",
      "options": [
        {
          "option_id": 1,
          "text": "Maria Sklodowska",
          "is_correct": true
        },
        {
          "option_id": 2,
          "text": "Anna Kowalski",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 3,
          "text": "Helena Nowak",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 4,
          "text": "Sofia Petrova",
          "is_correct": false
        }
      ],
      "answer": "Maria Sklodowska"
    },
    {
      "question_id": 4,
      "question_type": "MCQ",
      "question": "Where was Marie Curie born?",
      "options": [
        {
          "option_id": 1,
          "text": "Paris",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 2,
          "text": "Warsaw",
          "is_correct": true
        },
        {
          "option_id": 3,
          "text": "London",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 4,
          "text": "Berlin",
          "is_correct": false
        }
      ],
      "answer": "Warsaw"
    },
    {
      "question_id": 5,
      "question_type": "MCQ",
      "question": "Which university did Marie study at in Paris?",
      "options": [
        {
          "option_id": 1,
          "text": "Oxford",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 2,
          "text": "Cambridge",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 3,
          "text": "Sorbonne",
          "is_correct": true
        },
        {
          "option_id": 4,
          "text": "Harvard",
          "is_correct": false
        }
      ],
      "answer": "Sorbonne"
    },
    {
      "question_id": 6,
      "question_type": "MCQ",
      "question": "Who was Marie Curie’s husband?",
      "options": [
        {
          "option_id": 1,
          "text": "Henri Becquerel",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 2,
          "text": "Pierre Curie",
          "is_correct": true
        },
        {
          "option_id": 3,
          "text": "Louis Pasteur",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 4,
          "text": "Albert Einstein",
          "is_correct": false
        }
      ],
      "answer": "Pierre Curie"
    },
    {
      "question_id": 7,
      "question_type": "MCQ",
      "question": "Which mineral did the Curies work with to extract radium?",
      "options": [
        {
          "option_id": 1,
          "text": "Coal",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 2,
          "text": "Pitchblende",
          "is_correct": true
        },
        {
          "option_id": 3,
          "text": "Quartz",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 4,
          "text": "Granite",
          "is_correct": false
        }
      ],
      "answer": "Pitchblende"
    },
    {
      "question_id": 8,
      "question_type": "MCQ",
      "question": "What were the two elements discovered by the Curies?",
      "options": [
        {
          "option_id": 1,
          "text": "Uranium and Helium",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 2,
          "text": "Radium and Polonium",
          "is_correct": true
        },
        {
          "option_id": 3,
          "text": "Gold and Silver",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 4,
          "text": "Iron and Copper",
          "is_correct": false
        }
      ],
      "answer": "Radium and Polonium"
    },
    {
      "question_id": 9,
      "question_type": "MCQ",
      "question": "Polonium was named after:",
      "options": [
        {
          "option_id": 1,
          "text": "A scientist",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 2,
          "text": "A river",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 3,
          "text": "Marie’s country Poland",
          "is_correct": true
        },
        {
          "option_id": 4,
          "text": "A city",
          "is_correct": false
        }
      ],
      "answer": "Marie’s country Poland"
    },
    {
      "question_id": 10,
      "question_type": "MCQ",
      "question": "Who first discovered radioactivity in uranium?",
      "options": [
        {
          "option_id": 1,
          "text": "Pierre Curie",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 2,
          "text": "Henri Becquerel",
          "is_correct": true
        },
        {
          "option_id": 3,
          "text": "Newton",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 4,
          "text": "Faraday",
          "is_correct": false
        }
      ],
      "answer": "Henri Becquerel"
    },
    {
      "question_id": 11,
      "question_type": "MCQ",
      "question": "What condition did the Curies live in while researching?",
      "options": [
        {
          "option_id": 1,
          "text": "Luxury",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 2,
          "text": "Comfort",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 3,
          "text": "Extreme poverty",
          "is_correct": true
        },
        {
          "option_id": 4,
          "text": "Royal support",
          "is_correct": false
        }
      ],
      "answer": "Extreme poverty"
    },
    {
      "question_id": 12,
      "question_type": "MCQ",
      "question": "What gift did the Curies receive from the Emperor of Austria?",
      "options": [
        {
          "option_id": 1,
          "text": "Money",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 2,
          "text": "A laboratory",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 3,
          "text": "A ton of pitchblende",
          "is_correct": true
        },
        {
          "option_id": 4,
          "text": "A house",
          "is_correct": false
        }
      ],
      "answer": "A ton of pitchblende"
    },
    {
      "question_id": 13,
      "question_type": "MCQ",
      "question": "In which year was radium finally discovered?",
      "options": [
        {
          "option_id": 1,
          "text": "1895",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 2,
          "text": "1902",
          "is_correct": true
        },
        {
          "option_id": 3,
          "text": "1906",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 4,
          "text": "1911",
          "is_correct": false
        }
      ],
      "answer": "1902"
    },
    {
      "question_id": 14,
      "question_type": "MCQ",
      "question": "For which discovery did the Curies receive the Nobel Prize in 1903?",
      "options": [
        {
          "option_id": 1,
          "text": "Radium and Polonium",
          "is_correct": true
        },
        {
          "option_id": 2,
          "text": "Electricity",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 3,
          "text": "Gravity",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 4,
          "text": "X-rays",
          "is_correct": false
        }
      ],
      "answer": "Radium and Polonium"
    },
    {
      "question_id": 15,
      "question_type": "MCQ",
      "question": "Why did Marie refuse to patent radium?",
      "options": [
        {
          "option_id": 1,
          "text": "She disliked wealth",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 2,
          "text": "She believed it belonged to people",
          "is_correct": true
        },
        {
          "option_id": 3,
          "text": "She feared misuse",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 4,
          "text": "She was advised not to",
          "is_correct": false
        }
      ],
      "answer": "She believed it belonged to people"
    },
    {
      "question_id": 16,
      "question_type": "MCQ",
      "question": "How did Pierre Curie die?",
      "options": [
        {
          "option_id": 1,
          "text": "Illness",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 2,
          "text": "Accident with a horse-drawn wagon",
          "is_correct": true
        },
        {
          "option_id": 3,
          "text": "War",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 4,
          "text": "Old age",
          "is_correct": false
        }
      ],
      "answer": "Accident with a horse-drawn wagon"
    },
    {
      "question_id": 17,
      "question_type": "MCQ",
      "question": "For which subject did Marie receive the second Nobel Prize?",
      "options": [
        {
          "option_id": 1,
          "text": "Physics",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 2,
          "text": "Biology",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 3,
          "text": "Chemistry",
          "is_correct": true
        },
        {
          "option_id": 4,
          "text": "Medicine",
          "is_correct": false
        }
      ],
      "answer": "Chemistry"
    },
    {
      "question_id": 18,
      "question_type": "MCQ",
      "question": "What medical use of radium is mentioned?",
      "options": [
        {
          "option_id": 1,
          "text": "Curing flu",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 2,
          "text": "Treating cancer",
          "is_correct": true
        },
        {
          "option_id": 3,
          "text": "Improving eyesight",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 4,
          "text": "Reducing pain",
          "is_correct": false
        }
      ],
      "answer": "Treating cancer"
    },
    {
      "question_id": 19,
      "question_type": "MCQ",
      "question": "What quality best describes Marie Curie?",
      "options": [
        {
          "option_id": 1,
          "text": "Pride",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 2,
          "text": "Courage and determination",
          "is_correct": true
        },
        {
          "option_id": 3,
          "text": "Laziness",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 4,
          "text": "Arrogance",
          "is_correct": false
        }
      ],
      "answer": "Courage and determination"
    },
    {
      "question_id": 20,
      "question_type": "MCQ",
      "question": "What did Marie say about radium?",
      "options": [
        {
          "option_id": 1,
          "text": "It belongs to me",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 2,
          "text": "It belongs to the people",
          "is_correct": true
        },
        {
          "option_id": 3,
          "text": "It is dangerous",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 4,
          "text": "It is priceless",
          "is_correct": false
        }
      ],
      "answer": "It belongs to the people"
    },
    {
      "question_id": 21,
      "question_type": "MCQ",
      "question": "What does ‘penury’ mean in the lesson?",
      "options": [
        {
          "option_id": 1,
          "text": "Comfort",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 2,
          "text": "Extreme poverty",
          "is_correct": true
        },
        {
          "option_id": 3,
          "text": "Wealth",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 4,
          "text": "Luxury",
          "is_correct": false
        }
      ],
      "answer": "Extreme poverty"
    },
    {
      "question_id": 22,
      "question_type": "MCQ",
      "question": "Which prize did Marie win twice?",
      "options": [
        {
          "option_id": 1,
          "text": "Pulitzer",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 2,
          "text": "Booker",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 3,
          "text": "Nobel Prize",
          "is_correct": true
        },
        {
          "option_id": 4,
          "text": "Ramon Magsaysay",
          "is_correct": false
        }
      ],
      "answer": "Nobel Prize"
    },
    {
      "question_id": 23,
      "question_type": "MCQ",
      "question": "What was Marie’s major at university?",
      "options": [
        {
          "option_id": 1,
          "text": "History",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 2,
          "text": "Physics and Mathematics",
          "is_correct": true
        },
        {
          "option_id": 3,
          "text": "Biology",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 4,
          "text": "Literature",
          "is_correct": false
        }
      ],
      "answer": "Physics and Mathematics"
    },
    {
      "question_id": 24,
      "question_type": "MCQ",
      "question": "What does the lesson mainly highlight?",
      "options": [
        {
          "option_id": 1,
          "text": "Scientific formulas",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 2,
          "text": "Courage, dedication and humanity",
          "is_correct": true
        },
        {
          "option_id": 3,
          "text": "Adventure",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 4,
          "text": "Entertainment",
          "is_correct": false
        }
      ],
      "answer": "Courage, dedication and humanity"
    },
    {
      "question_id": 25,
      "question_type": "MCQ",
      "question": "What is the overall message of the lesson?",
      "options": [
        {
          "option_id": 1,
          "text": "Wealth is important",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 2,
          "text": "Hard work and selflessness serve humanity",
          "is_correct": true
        },
        {
          "option_id": 3,
          "text": "Science is easy",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 4,
          "text": "Luck decides everything",
          "is_correct": false
        }
      ],
      "answer": "Hard work and selflessness serve humanity"
    },
    {
      "question_id": 26,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "Who was Marie Curie?",
      "answer": "Marie Curie was a famous scientist and the discoverer of radium."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 27,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What was her original name?",
      "answer": "Her original name was Maria Sklodowska."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 28,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "Where was she born?",
      "answer": "She was born in Warsaw, Poland."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 29,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "Why did she go to Paris?",
      "answer": "To study science at the Sorbonne."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 30,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "Which subjects did she major in?",
      "answer": "Physics and Mathematics."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 31,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "Who was her husband?",
      "answer": "Pierre Curie."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 32,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What mineral did the Curies work with?",
      "answer": "Pitchblende."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 33,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "Which two elements did they discover?",
      "answer": "Radium and Polonium."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 34,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "Why was Polonium named so?",
      "answer": "In honour of her country Poland."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 35,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "Who discovered radioactivity in uranium?",
      "answer": "Henri Becquerel."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 36,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What kind of life did the Curies lead?",
      "answer": "A life of extreme poverty and hardship."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 37,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What gift did they receive from the Austrian emperor?",
      "answer": "A ton of pitchblende."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 38,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "In which year was radium discovered?",
      "answer": "1902."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 39,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "Why was the discovery of radium important?",
      "answer": "Because it had powerful medical uses."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 40,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "How is radium used in medicine?",
      "answer": "It is used to treat cancer."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 41,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "Why did Marie refuse to patent radium?",
      "answer": "She believed it belonged to humanity."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 42,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "When did Pierre Curie die?",
      "answer": "In 1906."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 43,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "How did Pierre die?",
      "answer": "He was killed in a road accident."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 44,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "When did Marie receive her second Nobel Prize?",
      "answer": "In 1911."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 45,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "For which subject was the second Nobel Prize awarded?",
      "answer": "Chemistry."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 46,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What does ‘penury’ mean?",
      "answer": "Extreme poverty."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 47,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What does ‘indomitable’ mean?",
      "answer": "Unbeatable in spirit."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 48,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What quality drove Marie’s work?",
      "answer": "Strong determination."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 49,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "Why was Marie’s university life difficult?",
      "answer": "Because of poverty and hunger."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 50,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What was Marie’s childhood dream?",
      "answer": "To study science in Paris."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 51,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What kind of laboratory did the Curies work in?",
      "answer": "A small, shabby shed."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 52,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What proved Marie’s will power?",
      "answer": "She continued working despite illness and poverty."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 53,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "Why was the gift of pitchblende precious?",
      "answer": "It was essential for extracting radium."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 54,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What did Marie say about wealth?",
      "answer": "She worked for science, not for money."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 55,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What does ‘incalculable’ mean?",
      "answer": "Too great to be measured."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 56,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What does ‘disconsolate’ mean?",
      "answer": "Very sad or depressed."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 57,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "Why is Marie called a brave heart?",
      "answer": "For her courage in hardship."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 58,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What was the Curies’ living condition?",
      "answer": "Utter penury and hardship."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 59,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What did radium look like?",
      "answer": "A tiny pinch of white powder."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 60,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What colour of light was seen from radium?",
      "answer": "Soft bluish purple."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 61,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "Why did Marie faint often?",
      "answer": "Due to hunger and lack of food."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 62,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What quality did Marie and Pierre share?",
      "answer": "Dedication to science."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 63,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "Why was Marie an exceptional scientist?",
      "answer": "Because of her courage and selflessness."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 64,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What does ‘compulsive desire’ mean?",
      "answer": "An uncontrollable urge."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 65,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What did Marie do after her husband’s death?",
      "answer": "She continued her scientific work."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 66,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "Why is Marie an example of humanity?",
      "answer": "She gave her discovery freely to the world."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 67,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What is the main theme of the lesson?",
      "answer": "Courage, dedication and service to humanity."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 68,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What did the Nobel Prize recognize?",
      "answer": "Their discovery of radium and polonium."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 69,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "Why did the Curies not live in luxury?",
      "answer": "They sacrificed comforts for research."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 70,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What is radioactivity?",
      "answer": "The emission of powerful rays from elements."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 71,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What does ‘hostile conditions’ refer to?",
      "answer": "Adverse living and working conditions."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 72,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What does the lesson teach students?",
      "answer": "Hard work and selflessness lead to greatness."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 73,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "Why is Marie admired worldwide?",
      "answer": "For her scientific contributions and character."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 74,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What was Marie’s attitude to success?",
      "answer": "Humble and devoted to humanity."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 75,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What moral does the story convey?",
      "answer": "True courage lies in dedication to a noble cause."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 76,
      "question_type": "LONG",
      "question": "Describe the early life and education of Marie Curie.",
      "answer": "Marie Curie, born Maria Sklodowska in Warsaw, Poland, grew up in poverty. Her dream was to study science in Paris, but financial difficulties delayed it. She worked as a governess to save money and later studied at the Sorbonne. Despite hunger and hardship, she topped her class in Physics and Mathematics, showing remarkable determination."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 77,
      "question_type": "LONG",
      "question": "Explain how Marie Curie and Pierre Curie discovered radium.",
      "answer": "The Curies worked with pitchblende to extract uranium. Marie noticed that the residue was even more powerful. After years of labor under difficult conditions, they discovered two new elements, Polonium and Radium. In 1902, they finally isolated radium, observing its soft bluish glow in the dark laboratory."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 78,
      "question_type": "LONG",
      "question": "What hardships did the Curies face during their research?",
      "answer": "They lived in extreme poverty, lacked proper food and warm clothing, and worked in a small, poorly equipped shed. Marie often fainted from hunger and illness, yet they continued their work with unwavering dedication."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 79,
      "question_type": "LONG",
      "question": "Discuss the scientific and medical importance of radium.",
      "answer": "Radium emits powerful rays that can penetrate substances. It has immense medical value, especially in treating cancer and killing harmful bacteria. Its discovery opened new avenues in medicine and science."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 80,
      "question_type": "LONG",
      "question": "Why did Marie Curie refuse to patent radium?",
      "answer": "Marie believed that scientific discoveries should benefit humanity. She said, ‘Radium belongs to the people, not to me.’ Her refusal to patent shows her selflessness and commitment to the welfare of mankind."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 81,
      "question_type": "LONG",
      "question": "Describe Pierre Curie’s contribution and his tragic death.",
      "answer": "Pierre Curie worked alongside Marie in their research and shared her passion for science. In 1906, he died in a road accident involving a horse-drawn wagon. Despite her grief, Marie continued their scientific work with courage."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 82,
      "question_type": "LONG",
      "question": "How does the lesson portray courage?",
      "answer": "The lesson portrays courage as mental strength to endure hardship. Marie faced poverty, illness and personal loss but remained dedicated to her mission, exemplifying true bravery."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 83,
      "question_type": "LONG",
      "question": "What qualities made Marie Curie an exceptional scientist?",
      "answer": "Her determination, endurance, humility, and dedication to humanity set her apart. She pursued knowledge despite hostile conditions and used her discoveries for the good of all."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 84,
      "question_type": "LONG",
      "question": "Explain the significance of the Nobel Prizes awarded to Marie Curie.",
      "answer": "In 1903, she received the Nobel Prize in Physics for discovering radium and polonium. In 1911, she won the Nobel Prize in Chemistry for her further work on radioactive elements, becoming the first woman to win twice."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 85,
      "question_type": "LONG",
      "question": "How does the lesson highlight service to humanity?",
      "answer": "By refusing wealth and sharing her discoveries freely, Marie exemplifies service to humanity. Her work saved lives and advanced medical science."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 86,
      "question_type": "LONG",
      "question": "What role did determination play in Marie Curie’s success?",
      "answer": "Determination enabled her to overcome poverty, illness and obstacles. It kept her focused on her goals and led to groundbreaking discoveries."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 87,
      "question_type": "LONG",
      "question": "Describe the living conditions of the Curie family.",
      "answer": "They lived simply with minimal furniture and worked in a dilapidated shed. Winters were harsh, food was scarce, and comfort was sacrificed for research."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 88,
      "question_type": "LONG",
      "question": "Why is Marie Curie called ‘A Brave Heart Dedicated to Science and Humanity’?",
      "answer": "She devoted her entire life to scientific discovery and used her work for the benefit of mankind, showing courage, compassion and selflessness."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 89,
      "question_type": "LONG",
      "question": "How did the gift of pitchblende change the Curies’ work?",
      "answer": "The gift provided the essential material needed to continue their experiments, enabling the eventual isolation of radium."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 90,
      "question_type": "LONG",
      "question": "What message does the lesson give about wealth and success?",
      "answer": "True success lies in service and integrity, not in wealth. Marie chose humanity over personal gain."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 91,
      "question_type": "LONG",
      "question": "Explain the importance of endurance in achieving greatness.",
      "answer": "Endurance helped Marie persist through years of hardship. Without it, her discoveries would not have been possible."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 92,
      "question_type": "LONG",
      "question": "How did Marie Curie balance personal loss with professional duty?",
      "answer": "After Pierre’s death, she grieved deeply but continued her work, showing extraordinary strength and commitment."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 93,
      "question_type": "LONG",
      "question": "What does the lesson teach about women in science?",
      "answer": "It shows that women can achieve greatness in science through determination and hard work."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 94,
      "question_type": "LONG",
      "question": "Discuss the theme of sacrifice in the lesson.",
      "answer": "The Curies sacrificed comfort, health and wealth for scientific progress, highlighting the nobility of self-sacrifice."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 95,
      "question_type": "LONG",
      "question": "How did Marie Curie’s discoveries impact the world?",
      "answer": "Her work advanced science and medicine, particularly in cancer treatment, saving countless lives."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 96,
      "question_type": "LONG",
      "question": "What values should students learn from Marie Curie’s life?",
      "answer": "Students should learn perseverance, humility, dedication and service to humanity."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 97,
      "question_type": "LONG",
      "question": "Why is Marie Curie a role model for humanity?",
      "answer": "Her selfless use of knowledge and tireless pursuit of truth make her an enduring role model."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 98,
      "question_type": "LONG",
      "question": "How does the lesson define true courage?",
      "answer": "True courage is the strength of mind to face adverse conditions and continue striving for a noble cause."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 99,
      "question_type": "LONG",
      "question": "What is the relevance of this lesson today?",
      "answer": "In a world driven by material success, it reminds us of the value of integrity, dedication and service."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 100,
      "question_type": "LONG",
      "question": "Write an appreciation of the lesson.",
      "answer": "‘A Brave Heart Dedicated to Science And Humanity’ is an inspiring account of Marie Curie’s life. It beautifully highlights courage, perseverance and selflessness. The lesson motivates readers to pursue knowledge with integrity and to use achievements for the greater good. Marie Curie stands as a timeless symbol of dedication to science and humanity."
    }
  ]
}